All right, Madam Clerk.
Well, it's actually Mr. City Manager.
I think we're going to hear from you-
Yes
... right now. Thank you.
So the next item on public hearing is our presentation from the city manager
for the proposed fiscal year 2027 budget.
Okay. Mayor, councilors,
once again, presentation of the city's annual budget, and as you heard
before, the school department tentatively will be presenting
their share of the budget, not tonight, but next week.
So two quick updates before I dive in.
Start with some good news. There is a lower tax rate increase than
we initially had projected. We updated some of the valuation numbers
due to new growth. This has nothing to do with
revaluations or this is actual new building, new construction.
And that means that instead of a 6% overall tax rate increase, it's now
at 5.1%. Of course, the final valuation number from the
assessor is never known until late July, sometimes August, sometimes
September, after they finish up their valuation work.
But unless money's added to the budget, the tax rate won't increase from that and
may actually decrease because there's more value that's found.
Second, in this presentation, the school budget numbers have been updated
as of March 23rd, so two weeks ago.
That's actually more up-to-date than what is in the budget books
that you all have, so I'm going to be referring to those numbers.
Of course, the school board hasn't actually voted yet to
approve a budget to send to the council, so that's also to be
taken with a grain of salt.
I always like to start this presentation to show what the trends are for
city services, what are the demands, what's the public
seeking, asking for. And as you'll see in just
about every category, the response is
sometimes flat but often up.
So for example, our police department last year responded to
32,234 calls. That's up
20% from 2023. It includes
nearly 7,600 traffic stops and nearly 700
calls involving mental health and behavioral health
liaisons. Our fire department responded to
5,742 calls. That's up 5.2% from
2023, and they also completed
1,206 life safety inspections, up
125% from the year before.
Our library users borrowed 16% more physical books than they
did two years ago, borrowed 62% more e-books and
digital books than they did last year, and there were 21% more
visitors who attended one or more programs at the library than they
did the year before.
My favorite or maybe least favorite one, city staff
received over 3.1 million emails.
That is up 55% from 2023. There are just
a lot of people emailing for service now.
Our IT help desk resolved nearly 6,900 tickets and
phone support issues. That's up 17% from the prior year.
Public works responded to 712 online work orders, up
34% from two years ago. They repaired 103
streetlights, similar to 2023.
They responded to 57 more traffic signal complaints,
40 overnight storms year to date. That's up 38%
from the same period two years ago.
And they repaired 119 potholes. That's actually down from last
year. However, it doesn't mean that they decided to not
fix potholes. It means that many of the ones that they
repaired, they didn't just do a cold patch on, they
fixed the underlying issue, so they are no longer potholes.
Our finance department processed over 16,000 vehicle
registrations. That's up 23% over the past three years.
Economic development tracked over 200 projects
during the course of the year. Our water resource protection plant
pumped and treated 1.75 billion gallons of
wastewater. That's actually down from 2.1 billion the
year before. But they treated and disposed of 4,900
tons of sludge, which is up 2.1% from
2024. They also cleaned nearly 2,800 catch basins,
and that prevented about 266 tons of sediment from entering
local water sources.
Code enforcement issued nearly 2,000 permits.
That's up 3% from two years ago. Our planning department
presented 15 ordinance
amendments and processed 59 applications.
That's down 36% from 2023. It should be noted
that things like ADUs moved to code-only review, however.
This fiscal year to date, our SPCTV crew
broadcast and streamed 92 meetings.
That's up 26% from the same time last year, and they produced
28.2% more productions
during that same period as well.
Wrapping up here, our sustainability office engaged with over 1,800
residents through different events like the Repair Fair, Earth Day, Swap Series,
and 13,000 residents through sustainability programs like
the Swap Shop, which averages 101 visits per day, the
Resilient Yards program, and the Electric Tool Library,
which had 360 checkouts last calendar year, up
11% from 2023.Our social
service office processed 1,319 applications
for general assistance. That's down 24% from
2024, but still up 57% from
2019. You all may recall during COVID, we had a pretty big
spike with the hotels being filled,
and the economic situation there, but as those hotels dissipated,
the numbers
did as well, but still up significantly from
pre-COVID times.
And last but not least, Parks and Rec.
Our park rangers spent over 1,000 hours in parks and ran 98
educational programs that had over 3,000 participants.
Our senior center hosted over 3,400 visitors and held 25
classes and workshops. Our all-girls sports camp maxed out
at 45 participants. That's up 255% from
2023. And over 17,000
patrons used the indoor walking track at the community center, and over
27,000 participants took part in our adult and youth open
gyms.
So the conclusion remains that resident demand for and use of city
services is strong and increasing.
With that in mind, the budget was prepared with three primary objectives.
To one, continue to provide the high-quality public services that our
community expects. Two, to address council's adopted goals
for 2026. And three, minimize the impact on taxpayers
and submit a budget that falls within the guidance given by city council.
So for that first objective, our FY27 budget,
it's kind of plain. It maintains current level of service while making
limited operational adjustments,
necessary to remain within the guidance that you all had provided a few months
back.
While many new positions could be justified, none of the eight new
positions that were requested by departments are included in this
budget to help address objective number three regarding the tax
rate. And in fact, three positions, two full-time, one
half-time, have been cut in the proposed budget.
Addressing your goals for 2027, several
goals weren't necessarily applicable to budget. Some were.
Many are addressed in the capital improvement budget, where there's funding for
initial implementation of the comprehensive plan,
as well as several related master plans as a goal of the
council was to see those plans implemented.
Another goal was to do more outreach, support outreach
to residents with information. So in addition to the
tax bill insert that we send late summer to all taxpayers,
we have funding for one additional informational mailing that we'd send probably
sometime around January or February to contain
additional information about things going on in the
city. This is a very small attempt to make up for the loss of "The
Century," which as we all know, was a source of information about
city ongoings for quite a bit of the population.
Our budget does continue to offer the tax rebates to several housing
developers that are providing affordable housing.
In addition, the Affordable Housing Committee has requested half a million dollars
to be placed in the Affordable Housing Trust Fund.
Objective three, minimize the impact on taxpayers and submit a budget within
guidance given by the council. So at that February workshop, you told the
city,
shoot for a 3% to 5% tax increase, with
many councilors closer to that middle number of 4%, and your guidance
to the school was between 3% to 6%. So the municipal share of the
tax rate increase is 3%, which is at the low end of
council guidance. The proposed overall taxes to
be raised when factoring in city, school, county, and metro is
up 69 cents. Again, that's a 5.1% increase.
And so that's another way we help to meet council's
goal.
We also didn't fund any new positions as your guidance was not to fund
any that couldn't be offset with...
Or at least positions that couldn't be offset with other expenses or new revenues
were not funded.
So starting off in our process when,
we accounted for the fixed costs, electricity, fuel,
all those things, and initial department budget requests,
it would've resulted in just the city's share of the budget
alone, an increase to the tax rate of 70 cents or
14.5% increase on our portion of the tax
rate. So that translates, when you look at the overall tax rate, that
in and of itself would've been a 5.1% increase.
Again, not including county, metro, or school, and we knew that was definitely
not something that was acceptable.
Some of the cost drivers did include those eight new positions that had been
requested. There's $1.3 million in wage increases due to
union contracts, COLA increases, et cetera.
A 10% jump in health insurance,
$76,000
increase in electricity costs, over $150,000
increase in waste disposal and recycling,
contractual expenses, and even our dispatch costs were up
over $62,000. So that's kind of some of the drivers that we
faced going into the budget,
our budget review. So that meant in order to get to a tax increase
that was no greater than 4%, we needed to find nearly
3.45 million in cuts or new revenues to get there.
So how'd we do that? Well, it effectively worked out.
We didn't intend it this way, but
we split the baby, so to speak. There was about 1.7 million
in increased revenue, so we got some great news
about state revenue sharing, an additional 1.35 million.
We'll talk about that a little bit more later.
Our investment income is doing well, so well that we conservatively
thought we could bump that up by $100,000.
In excise tax revenue, folks keep buying cars and trucks, and
so, we felt comfortable inching that up by
$200,000 as well. So all those things, and
others, totaled at 1.7, and we also reduced costs by
1.7 million. That was not funding the eight new positions.
That saved over $700,000. We eliminated two and a half
existing positions, which saved about $160,000.
And we were unable to purchase one new PD patrol vehicle, which
saved about $75,000, in addition to several
other... cuts that were made.
So overall, when you look at all that, if you look at the general fund, which is
comprised of the school, municipal, county, and metro budget,
the enterprise fund, which in our case is the sewer budget, and then special
revenue funds, which is golf, SPCTV.
All of those in total are up seven million to
$147,716,535.
That's a 5% increase in spending overall.
When you look at just the general fund share of those expenses, the school
accounts for 55% of the expenses,
municipal 42, county and metro 3%.
But this is a lot different than how tax dollars are
allocated, and we'll talk about why in just a minute here.
As I said before, the municipal budget's kind of plain.
There's not a lot exciting in it. It was, in many ways, a status quo budget,
just given the budget circumstances that the city faces, including
the impending building needs. We were able to do some good things in it,
however. We increased the senior property tax relief program
again. Council significantly increased that over the years, so that's
another increase to provide more assistance to
qualifying seniors.
There's some investment in cybersecurity that we're making.
We've been doing a really good job of that over the years, and
we're going to continue with even more this year.
We have a $9,000 grant match programmed in to help with home energy
assessments for low-income homeowners to help
them audit and find ways to save money on their energy bills.
Continued funding for a modest board and committee recognition event in line with
council's goal of
providing support to committees.
There's some bumps in temporary staffing across recreation, youth
program, camps, and senior program budgets to
maintain availability and competitive wages for staff in those areas.
Some cases even offer expanded service, such as no-cost or
low-cost programming for seniors.
And then we talked about that mailer that's being added to help provide
better information to the public.
Wanted to highlight new this year, committee
requests. They used to appear in the department in which
their committee liaison works, so planning board would
appear in the planning budget. That all changed this year.
Council updated its policy, and so now all operating
requests from committees, and those requests have to be $2,500 or
less, those show up in the council's budget.
I can still review those and make recommendations. I've reviewed all of them.
I recommend full funding that each of them requested, and so that is
in the budget proposal.
Another category was created this year called special request item.
These are for one-time and/or non-operating items.
They're not limited to $2,500. I don't review these
per the policy, and they're also not automatically included in the budget.
They're something that, during the budget workshops, you all will
have to determine whether or not they're something you want to add into the budget.
And I won't get into the details now, although they are in your budget books, but
we've had five committees request $560,000
in combined special requests. And so you'll, on the 28th, when you talk about
your council department budget,
we'll provide guidance on those.
So let's talk about revenues and expenses.
So revenues, when we're looking at new growth and non-property tax
revenues,
we're estimating right now $20 million in new growth.
That means about $270,000 in new tax
revenue. A bulk of that goes to the school department.
The city gets to keep a smaller amount to put towards
the costs that are increasing to help keep the tax rate down.
Significantly this year, though, it's the other sources of revenue that are up
12.8%, or $2.9 million. And again, the biggest one
there is state revenue sharing.
And actually, I guess maybe here I'll talk about that.
So state revenue sharing, just quickly, because this is important, it's
broken into two components, Rev 1 and Rev 2.
Rev 1, essentially everybody gets.
Rev 2 is only given to communities that
have high mill rates, or it has to be at a
certain amount or above. And for the past several years,
to the surprise of some, I'm sure, South Portland's mill rate has been below that
threshold. So we have gotten $0 in Rev 2,
while other communities with higher tax rates have gotten
higher amounts. This year, for the first time in several years, we
barely squeaked over that mark, and we qualified for Rev
2, and that's about $820,000.
That's great news this year, but if next year our tax rate doesn't go
up enough to whatever the state adjusts it to next year, we lose all of
that. So that's just a caution I'll also talk about later.
But for this year, it's a good shot in the arm.
Our fund balance is another source of revenue.
It's the difference between total city assets and liabilities,
and a component of that fund balance is unassigned, which means there's been no
use
assigned to it, and there's no restrictions on those dollars.
Our policy says that in our unassigned fund balance, we need
to have between 9% to 12% of whatever the next
year's budget is going to be. So if it's a $100 million
budget, we need 9% to 12% of whatever that
number is to be kept in fund balance.
Any amounts over that 12% can be, and are, used
for one-time expenditures such as capital improvement projects.
So this year, as of June 30th of 2025, our unassigned fund
balance stood at 23.8 millionThat's
18.7%
of the proposed budget expenditures, so that gave us a pretty big
cushion between the 12% and the 18.7%
to use for operating and capital budget purchases.
So
how did we use it this year? In our FY27 budget, we're
using $250,000 towards the operating budget.
Essentially, what that does is it buys down the tax rate a little bit.
We've been using less and less
for that purpose over the past several years.
So for example, that amount is 29% less than this current budget
year, and 74% less than it was in FY23.
We're also using $300,000 for a one-time budget expense.
That's some of the more appropriate uses of fund balance,
because it's a one-time use of funds, and next year there's no expense,
and therefore, there's no expectation that fund balance covers that expense.
And then we were able to use just over $3 million towards our
CIP. So that totaled just about $4 million.
In addition, our finance director has set aside $3
million as an anticipated loan to the school
department, due to an anticipated budget overage that they'll
have to close out this current budget year.
So there's
overages that we're preparing for of about $2 million in their
operating budget, and about $1 million in their food service budget.
So again, about $3 million. We hope that's a high estimate, but
that's what we've plugged in there as can't spend because the
school will run out of their own fund balance, and then the only
other source is to dip into ours.
So that all brings our balance down to $17.1 million.
So that means we're at 12.8% of our proposed expenditures.
And I probably won't talk about it now, but maybe I will because I don't know if I
do later. But one of the important reasons that we are actually
recommending staying above that 12% is
because next year when we go into the
capital budget season, if first of all, if council increases the
budget, let's say, "Hey, school go ahead and spend more," that 9% to
12% range goes up, right? And so we're at
12.8% now, but if the school budget went up enough, for example,
that might now only be 12%. So we've got to give ourselves a little wiggle room.
The second reason would be
next year we need a base for purchases of CIP
items. We deferred a number of purchases this year because we set that $3
million aside. Next year, we're going to have to
consider funding those and a whole bunch of new items that we'll talk
about when we talk about the CIP. And so we need some seed money there
to fund those items because there's never a guarantee of how much we're going to
turn back at the end of this fiscal year.
It might not be enough to fund-- Well, it definitely won't be enough to fund
everything, but it might not be enough to fund a significant enough amount.
So when you look at our expenses, it's really four departments that make up about
70% of the budget. Police accounts for about
20%, fire about 19%, public work 17%, parks and rec
13%,
and then throw in debt for 4%. That means all other departments or
budget line items take up about 30% of the budget or about,
what's that? Maybe a percent and a half each
of the budget. So you can see where the city's priorities are by where those
dollars are allocated.
In terms of what budget categories are spent on, as you can imagine,
two-thirds of our costs are personnel.
Wages, benefits, that's really what we are. We're a people business.
We're a service sector
entity. And
the next closest expense amount is contractual, which is
only at 13%.
So how do we calculate then what we need from taxes?
So
the amount we need to raise from taxes is a math formula.
What are your expenses? Subtract your non-property tax revenue,
and that gives you the total need from property taxes or your tax commitment.
So you do that for the school, for the municipal budget, for the county
assessment, and the metro assessment.
And so all told there, you're looking at just over
$138 million in expenses. There's about
$41.6 million in non-property tax revenues,
and that means you have $96.4 million in
needs from property taxes, and that's a 5% increase
from last year. So how do you calculate the tax rate?
Well, you take that $96.4 million that you need to raise in
taxes, and you divide it by your community's total
taxable value. And so in South Portland's case, we're estimating
just over $6.7 billion, and that gives you the
0.01434. You multiply that by 1,000, that
gives you a mill rate of 1434.
Final number, again, won't be determined until the assessor completes his work in
hopefully late July.
So here are the individual components of the tax rate.
It's made up of the school, the municipal, the county, and the metro share.
So I like to point out this distinction each year.
So let's look at the municipal current tax rate is
$4.67 out of the overall $13.65
tax rate. So we're looking at a 14 cent increase
up to $4.81. So that jump from
$4.67 to $4.81 is a 3% increase. So that's where
we live within the council's guidance, and actually because of the new-- It was
originally 4%, but because of the new budget values that we found,
it's now only 3%. But the impact on the tax rate itself, so
that $13.65 number, a 14
cent increase is only 1%. So the actual impact on what someone's going to pay
in taxes is 1% more due to the city's budget.
It's 3.6% more as the school's budget currently
stands, and then between county and metro, it's just under a half a percent
for again, that total increase of
5.1%.So when you
pay $100, every $100 of the property tax bill that you pay, the
school gets $61.70. The municipal share of the
budget gets $33.50, and the county and metro gets $4.80.
Let's focus in just on that $33.50 that the
municipality gets.
Here's where that portion of
$33.50 goes. So $7.40 to police,
$6.20 to public works, $5.70 to fire, $2.90 to
parks and rec, $2.30 to debt, and then all other 17
departments share in $9.
What does this all mean for the average homeowner?
So the average valued home in South Portland is
$456,100. That's a $315
increase if you don't have the homestead, up to $6,540.
If you do have the homestead, it's a $297 increase up to
$6,182.
So based on that, let's say you don't get the homestead, the average tax bill of
$6,540,
just over $4,000 goes to the school, just under $2,200 goes to the
municipal share of the budget, $262 goes to
the county, and $52 goes to metro.
Another way to look at this, of the $2,191 that the city gets
from that tax bill, here's what
you pay for each department, and it starts from the police at $4.89 to
public works at $4.07 to fire to $3.78, all the way down
to city council, $20, legal budget, $11, and
poor Jessica is there at 10 o'clock, bringing $10,
bringing up the rear.
Tax rate comparison. So,
whether taxes are too high or too low or just right is obviously a
subjective thing for all individuals.
But there are several objective measures that can help us determine whether our tax
rate and our tax increases are consistent with or out of
sync with other communities and metrics, and so there's five different things I
like to look at each year.
Not any one of these things is the end-all be-all, but when you look at all
five of them in
aggregate, it helps to paint a pretty good picture.
And so the first one is the consumer price index.
It's a way to measure inflation. We use the CPI-U Northeast.
The CPI's changed in different regions of the country.
That one is most relevant to South Portland.
In 2025, that was 3.2%. Our
proposed 5.1 tax rate increase is higher than that
CPI-U Northeast.
When you compare us to abutting communities, so the FY26 tax
rate, our tax rate is a $1.12 higher than the
average of the four abutting communities, Cape, Portland, Scarborough,
and Westbrook. So you'll see only Westbrook is higher than ours.
The other three communities are lower.
However, this is why the tax rate doesn't tell the whole story.
Our median tax bill is over 10% lower than the
average tax bills of those communities.
So you can see that aside from Westbrook, all those other communities
have higher median tax bills. So Westbrook, with the highest tax
rate, has the lowest median tax bill.
So again, that all is due to the value of the median
home in those communities.
When you look at the tax commitment, so going through that process of
what are your expenses minus non-property tax revenues, what do you need to
raise in taxes? So I compare to when I started here in
FY18, how much has our needs from taxes
changed over that time compared to our abutting peers of
Westbrook, Scarborough, Portland, and Cape?
Out of comparing to all that, we rank the lowest for the percent change in
property taxes raised. We're 4.5 to
20.3 percentage point less than our
abutters. You can see we're kind of close to Scarborough, Portland, a little
bit to Cape, and then Westbrook is much higher than ours.
But we are the lowest.
When you compare us to the 10 largest communities in Maine,
again, why the tax rate doesn't tell the whole story, our tax rate is
$3.70 lower than the average. It's the third lowest
out of all these communities. But when you look at the median tax
bill,
it's $645 higher, 11.6%. We're the
fifth highest. We're right in the middle, and again, that has to do with the
value of the median home.
The final way to look at this is a full value tax rate.
This is a
exercise done by the state that helps you really better
compare communities' tax rates to one another because not everyone
assesses at the same percentages.
It values their properties at the same percentage, et cetera, so this tries to
equalize for that. So when you compare South Portland's full value tax
rate of 1320 in this case, this is 2024 data, the most recent
they had, you compare that to the average of all communities in Cumberland
County. We're $1.42 less than the average of all communities in
Cumberland County, and we're $1.84 less than the average of all
communities in Maine.
So what does this tell us? Well, the scorecard shows five checks in the green,
meaning we're lower
than
the metric
that we're looking at, and three red checks, meaning there's three areas where
we're higher. So I would conclude from this that overall,
our tax bills are in line with other communities, and there's been an ongoing
mindfulness to keep the mill rate in check over the
years.One last thing, I added this slide
last year. We often hear, "How come taxes have to go up every year?
Why they never stay flat? How come?" My answer to that is nothing ever stays
flat. Everything we're paying for over the past eight years, the tax
commitment's gone up 40%. Your Netflix subscription has gone up
80%. If you want to buy a pickup truck, it's now 43% more expensive.
Eggs are 124% more expensive. A two-liter of Pepsi is
77%. Happy Meal, 43%. So
yes, we do try to limit what we need to raise in
taxes each year, but all of these things get more expensive for the
city. And unless there's an articulated
desire to reduce a certain service beyond
what's currently there,
and there's not other revenues that increase at a significant
amount enough to offset those increases in expenses,
then property taxes unfortunately need to increase,
but just like pretty much everything else is increasing.
I do want to say in 2026, we've had a little bit of shock the past couple of years,
especially in 2024, where there were revals that occurred on
top of, or equalizations that occurred on top of the budget
increases. And so a lot of people that were expecting maybe a
6% increase are a 20%, 25% increase due to the value of their
homes. Just remember, we collected no additional money.
Some people paid more, some didn't.
We'll see this year the typical tweaks to certain properties, like we
always have over the past 20-ish years.
So some might see that 5.1%, maybe it's 6%
or something to that effect, but others will see less.
It will be absolutely nothing like the catch-up effect from 2024.
So again, just a couple outlooks. Revenue sharing, it's volatile.
If we don't qualify next year, we lose $810,000.
That just puts us in a bigger budget hole next year, so we need to use caution
there. As you all know, we have tens and tens of millions in deferred
maintenance
at Central Fire, Police, Library, Hamlin, City Hall.
As of right now, we have a tentative plan to put a 2026 bond
question for the police and fire that'll address two of five of these.
That will add debt service payment to next year's budget if it's passed by voters,
or excuse me, to the FY28 budget. And that will impact the tax rate, but we'll
still have three buildings to somehow address.
We do use, even though it's a smaller amount than usual, $250K.
If we don't have any fund balance available for that, then
we'll have to find cuts or increase in taxes to make up for that.
And then although not part of the tax rate, as you all know, the Pearl Street pump
station and plant dewatering project will add significant
debt to water resources budget. There's going to be a 22%
increase in each of the next three years just to cover that debt.
So that's going to be a big hit out of the other pocket of the taxpayer that
pays the sewer bill.
Again, can't stress enough, we're looking for and have applied for congressional
earmarks and are looking at other sources such as TIF, and
ultimately we'll present something for the council's consideration as a way to
mitigate those increases.
Speaking of sewer,
the FY27 sewer enterprise budget is up
3.6%. Again, not property tax dollars, funded
primarily by sewer user fees. The sewer rate as a result will
increase by 4.1%. That equates to an $18
annual increase to the average homeowner.
But because at the time of the budget printing, we didn't know what the
impact of the Pearl Street dewatering project debt would be, this does not
yet include that 22% or anything else.
So we will be presenting to you over the course of the budget process
what we expect the actual increase to be, but we know it's at least
4.1%.
A reminder, South Portland maintains one of the lowest sewer rates in the
region. The typical residential bill
for surrounding communities is roughly 16% to 102% higher than
South Portland. So here,
we use the average of 600 cubic feet per month
and compared it to other Portland Water District communities.
So South Portland,
a home in that case would pay $44, Westbrook $51,
Wyndham $61, Gorham $68, Portland $78, Cumberland $86,
Cape $89. So we are
obviously going to put a dent in that pretty significantly with the Pearl
Street project, but other communities, if you look at the Water
District's plans for upgrades in some of those communities and
some of these communities' own upgrades, they're
also looking at capital projects
that are going to also have significant impacts on some of their rates as
well.
Again, these are costs that
reflect 50-year-old pieces of equipment that
were pretty much all installed in the 1970s and now
statewide, countrywide, are coming due for replacement, so we're not alone.
A couple of the highlights of this budget.
It does support expanded water quality monitoring at Willard Beach in
partnership with the DEP and EPA, and there are a number of projects which we'll
talk about in just a second that are included as part of their capital budget.
And then finally, for the special revenue fund, so golf course,
street openings, SPCTV, that's up
$153,000, 21.2%.
These are all entities which do not receive tax funding.
They're funded by their own fees or other sources.
Primarily, the big increase here is because the golf course is adding a
staff member. This allows them, through a whole
rejiggering of things, to create an additional park position
at no added cost to the tax rate because the costs are effectively
switched to the... golf course, and if people have questions,
I'll let Carl explain the convoluted mechanics of that.
SPCTV, so they're upgrading a current part-time position to full-time.
That is funded, however, by increased billable revenue and decrease in
other expenses that they made in order to be able to accommodate that.
As always, as we've been warning for the past few years, their budget right now is
funded by the Spectrum franchise fee.
So 5% of whatever the bills are in South Portland
for Spectrum TV, we get a check
every quarter, every half, whenever it is, from them.
So the less users, that goes down. That's certainly gone down
in the past 10 years as people have cut the cord.
They had built up a pretty good fund balance, but either by
next fiscal year or maybe the one thereafter, they will have
depleted their
fund balance and will either need to make significant cuts or start
putting a portion of their budget on the tax rate in order to continue the status
quo.
So our capital improvement plan, we'll go through this quickly and then wrap up.
This prioritizes short and long-range plans for land acquisition, equipment
replacement, and construction projects over a several year period.
The first year of the program, FY27, represents the proposed
capital budget for that fiscal year, and that's
technically what you're approving this year.
Even though you're approving the whole plan, you're only committing funding to the
first year of it. So requests, kind of like operating budget, they're made
by the departments to me.
I review them with the department director, the finance director, and then we try
to prioritize based on what are the city's objectives, priorities, what does the
comp plan have to say? Are there any special studies and reports?
Do you have an anticipated funding source?
A grant would make your project much more likely to be funded.
We received
77 requests from nine departments totaling
226.3 million. The number is very big this year
because facilities had put in
the cost for all the new city hall, library,
police, and fire. And so that debt service isn't showing up in the budget.
It's just here to show the costs for those things
somewhere.
Fifty-three of those 77 items relied either in whole or in
part on 6.2 million of proposed use
of unassigned fund balance. As you heard before, we only had about 3
million available for that,
so we had to cut 19 and partially fund one of these
projects, and that helped reduce the use of fund balance
by 3 million, and that got us to that
3.150 number
there.
So total of in addition to undesignated fund balance, there are reserves and grants
and other sources. We're able to fund 57 projects using all those different
sources. So I want to give you a highlight because I think this is where, unlike
the operating budget, we can be proud of some of the things we're able to fund this
year.
So in city facilities, again, the caveat here is
we've plugged in, we have
165.1 million in facilities needs.
There's no debt service in here. There's no commitment to the council to pay for
them. This is just a placeholder for when the council
decides on whatever next steps, and bonding will
require voter approval, so this is not a debt service assumption.
I can't say that enough.
We do need, unfortunately, to invest some money in existing facilities as we limp
along towards whatever final outcome we have for our buildings.
Our elevator, we've tried to hold off on repairs over the years.
We've done some minor repairs. Our facilities folks have MacGyvered some
parts because they don't make them anymore and haven't for years.
But it's at the point now where in order to maintain ADA compliance, we're going to
have to invest some money into it.
Same thing with the branch library bridge, if we want to maintain access to the
branch library, that is in need of repair.
Central air handling unit is needed at the community center, and we
desperately need
carbon dioxide and... What's NO2 again?
Nitric oxide.
Nitric oxide. I failed chemistry.
Detectors at municipal services.
For planning and infrastructure, we have money in there for Crockett's Corner
improvements, for Broadway Corridor pedestrian improvements,
comp plan implementation for Cash Corner Main Street, Maine Mall Master
Plan, coastal resilient zoning phase two, and a fiscal impact
of development tool. So basically, if a developer comes to us
with a project, we have an off-the-shelf tool that
says, "Okay, here's the impact that project's going to have on city
services and operating budgets" and all that.
So
I thought that would be helpful with a number of things in the pipeline.
Public safety, we're replacing a fire engine.
We're remounting Ambulance 44, purchasing a new
PD negotiator van and motorcycle, and also street
closure portable barriers.
For parks and public works, we have two new plow trucks, a
compact excavator. We're replacing a skid steer.
We have three replacement mowers for the golf course for different
parks, and also making improvements at
four different trails, the Greenbelt, Hinckley, and Pentuleck, totaling
275,000, and then Spring Point Shoreway totaling
60,000.
Finally, significant improvements at Willard Beach. We're replacing the playground.
We need some repairs to the snack shack.
A parking lot gate, which we may have some private funding for and it
aligns with our eventual paid parking plan.
A beach surf rake and Willard pump station
electrical upgrades.
For sewer and stormwater, this is the WRP budget.
The Pearl Street pump station and dewatering project are the
big ones. There's also the Main Street pump station force main
replacementOur annual sewer lining program and
chlorine storage tank replacements.
So again, as I pointed to earlier, fund balance is critical to fund
these CIP items. We wouldn't have been able to fund
most of what you just saw if we didn't have
enough fund balance in our coffers.
So an example of things this year we couldn't fund, because in part we had set
aside some money for school overages.
There's fencing upgrades in parks.
There's a truck and an ATV that parks needs to be replaced.
The truck's over
nearly 14 years old. There's a GPS field turf painter that
would save a ton of staff time and be able to focus our efforts
elsewhere. Significant Wainwright infrastructure improvements, a
parking study, a transportation master plan.
The list continues. And next year there are even
bigger items that we know of that without fund balance, we
may have a hard time funding. So these are cardiac monitors, SCBA
extractor, wireless access point for wireless connectivity in city
buildings,
upgrades to Pier Street and Legere Park playgrounds, a sweeper and a
loader for public works, various sidewalk improvements, street
light, smart controls, et cetera.
So just wanted to give you a flavor of some of the reasons why fund balance is
critical.
Don't need to spend much time here.
We've got about $70 million in future CIP through
FY33, mostly in the realm of environmental
protection, and I think, I'm spacing on this,
but I think that's a lot to do with water resource protection
investments that they'll be making over the next five years.
So you see most of that there goes to environmental.
I just want to remind folks at home that all of this information, the budget
information, including past audits, we're audited every year, it's
available on our website.
If you go to the budget page on our website, there's the capital
budget. There's a whole document for that. And then there's annual budgets.
You can look back at least 10 or 15 years for older budgets,
as shown there on the screen. The upcoming timeline, so next week
we have our first budget workshop. The schools will kick things off.
They'll also be presenting, like I did tonight, their share of the
budget. Council will be able to give guidance at that time, and then we'll resume
with the other city departments where you'll determine whether
things that you want to take out, add in, reduce, increase,
put those items in the budget parking lot.
And then on the 28th, you'll have your second workshop for all of the other
departments, including the first discussion topic of the
city council's budget with the committees.
You'll then be able to place things in the parking lot there.
And then
on May 12th, you'll have your final budget workshop, and that's where you'll
discuss all of those parking lot items and consider which ones,
again, you want to add, delete, increase, decrease, whatever.
The week before that, you have the public hearing and council approval of the
budget to send to voters. On June 9th is the school budget
referendum where voters will give the up or down to the school budget.
And on Tuesday, June 16th, there's final budget approval.
So at all these ones that are seen as council meetings, the workshops, the
public hearings, the final budget approval, the public, in addition tonight, gets a
chance to comment there. So members of the public, feel free to attend these
meetings and share your thoughts.
Thanks to department heads who are all here tonight in case there are questions.
I appreciate them for presenting responsible budgets.
And special thanks to our finance director, Ellen Sanborn, Deputy Finance Director
Rhonda Glidden, and our management and special projects associate, Draven Walker.
They put in awesome months of work on getting these documents
to you and to the public. So with that, I'm
happy to turn things back over to you, Mayor and Council.
But you can stay there if you wouldn't mind, Scott.
Okay.
I'll stay here.
So thank you, thank you very, very much.
Thank you to you personally, Scott.
This takes a lot to pull it together, and thank you to all the
department heads who have worked with you, and thank you to all of the
staff. I think
it's
quite clear when we see something like this, us residents, it's
a clear reminder of how much goes
on in our city any given day, throughout
the year. And we do really have the privilege of
a nicely high quality of life living in South Portland, and
that is not an accident. It takes a lot to keep a community
afloat, so thank you so much.
Generally, it's council practice to receive
this presentation tonight, but not to do a deep
dive. We have, as Scott pointed out, three more budget
meetings to do that. So I think I'd like to see
us keep to that practice. It doesn't mean councilors might not have
questions, but perhaps we limit our questions to a couple
each at this stage, and then I think we probably want
some of the members of the public want to make comment.
So councilors, questions. Councilor West.
My only question on this level is when are we supposed to talk about
the CIP issues?
When the individual department budget comes up, we talk about both their operating
and their CIP requests.
Okay.
Yep.
And then I'd add my thanks.
Okay.
Very good budget. Very responsible budget. Thank you.
Thank you. More questions, councilors?
Councilor Scott, yes.
I had a general question.
You talk about the difference or the valuation increase of about
$20 million, and I think it'd be very helpful for me as a new
councilor and for residents as we think about this budget and going forward,
what the difference is between a valuation
increaseVersus the
revaluation that happened in '26.
Yep.
Or '24, I'm sorry.
And how we as a city, thinking about both our budget and the school
budget, what does it mean to grow the value of
South Portland,
which is separate from a valuation readjustment, et cetera?
So if you could just give
a minute on that.
Yeah.
And then my other question was just in the, I think it's slide 28,
the
municipal expenses and then
non-property tax revenues. The non-property tax revenues
is substantial. I'm sure it's in the massive binder
that you have provided to me, and I've tried to look through every page.
But if you could just give a minute on that.
I think it's mostly sort of sewer, maybe, revenues.
What slide was that? What number was that again?
It's number 28.
I just think that's an important thing to highlight, that there is an expense
budget and then a revenue budget, and what that means.
So those are-
Sure
... my two very high level questions.
So I'll start. The valuation one's always a good one to talk about.
So
again, the misconception often is if we increase the value of your home, we're
somehow collecting more taxes everywhere.
And reality is, I hate to put it this bluntly,
because I know the assessor got criticized maybe when he said it this way, but
it's a math function. What we need to raise in taxes stays constant
during a revaluation. If we need $100 million in taxes,
when we do a revaluation and if most home
values are going up and business values are going up, the mill
rate's going to go down because we need less of a mill rate now that there's more
value to collect that same 90 million.
And I won't go into the explanation, but it creates winners and losers because
some people's properties go up way more than others.
Some people's don't go up very much.
And so,
it really shifts the burden of who's paying what
percent of that overall 100 million.
In the case of revaluations versus new value, so
revaluations, again, in that strict sense is
it's just you have your home, it's worth
300,000 today, but the assessor comes by and says, "Geez, we
haven't updated the value on this, and all the other
houses on your street within the past three years have sold for
700,000. Yours is comparable, so now your new value is 700,000." So
that's one way. That's not the new value we're talking about here, though.
What we're talking about here is someone went and built a brand new hotel, or they
built a brand new home, and so that's new tax dollars coming
into the community that didn't exist the year before.
And so those are the dollars that help when you have
increases in wages and health insurance.
That's the new revenue that can come in and help to offset that.
And as is the case in most communities this year, the
$270,000 that we got from that new value, it'll end up being a little bit
more, but we were conservative. That's nowhere near enough to
cover all the expenses. Just on the city side, we
had 1.3 million increases in wages due to
union contracts and COLAs. So that 270,000 in new
value,
just that alone, it doesn't even cover that.
So,
the more new value, the more new growth, the more revenue that comes in.
You have to be careful and do an analysis because if you
start building all these new things, there's impact on infrastructure, on roads,
on schools, so you have to do a careful analysis of when a project
comes in. All right, it's going to generate 100 million in new revenue,
but how much is it going to increase in expenses?
And then going back to your question on
other sources of...
If I can get to the right slide. Was it this one?
Yes.
This one here. So for the school, a big
one there is going to be your
state aid from education.
Yes.
So I don't know if that's all of that, but that's probably a pretty big chunk
of that. For the city, our
two largest sources after property taxes are
state revenue sharing and vehicle excise tax.
Those are the two
biggest non-property tax sources of revenues.
That accounts for a significant share of that.
There's other sources of licenses and fees and,
I'm trying to think of some other ones.
I don't know if there's any grant figures in here or not.
But typically speaking, it's property tax, vehicle
excise tax, and then state revenue sharing.
Thank you, Scott. I think the tax point is really important to keep
in mind and keep refreshing about the sort of the difference between
rebalancing versus growth and how we manage that going forward.
So I really appreciate that. Thank you. And great presentation.
Thanks.
Councilor Walker.
I had 11, but I'll pare it way down.
All right. Well, you will have a chance-
You've got lots of opportunities.
Yes
... next.
I know. Well, I have more for the other nights, too, but-
100 for the other nights, just 11 for tonight.
So for the county assessment,
I know that right now the final numbers aren't in yet.
Yeah.
If it's higher, will that push our tax rate higher, or would you be
looking to make cuts in other places to get us to still at that
7.3%?
Yeah. It's up to the
council, I guess, is the right answer.
Typically speaking, whether it's metro or the county assessment, we try not to
hold the school or municipalities, try to hold us harmless
for that because if their budget's going up, that doesn't mean we
have less needs or less expenses.
It's all part of the pot, but yeah, if they went up
significantly,
the two options are either raise taxes...
another cent to cover that increase or cut if it's
$100,000, find $100,000 in savings in the school or
municipal budget.
Okay. And then just two more. In line with that,
I know the school still doesn't have their health insurance premiums.
They're just estimating. Are we in the same boat? Are we estimating?
No, we have our numbers.
Okay.
We're different from there. It's essentially half a year though,
so we have to make some estimates, but it is-
Okay
... we are unfortunately locked in at 10%.
The good news is they have a much larger employee
population. So,
that number for them hurts a lot more.
Yeah.
10%'s not great, but 10% for the school would be a lot worse than it is for the
city.
And then for last one on estimating.
So I know that with the war in Iran, this is wreaking havoc with fuel
prices, which will eventually wreak havoc with food prices.
How do you factor that in when you're making these projections,
and has that changed since you started this work?
Yeah.
Or
neared completion of this work in February and early March.
Great question. So, that wasn't factored into the budget, just given the timing
of when-
Yeah
... this was due to the council and everything.
So ultimately what it means is if there are road
projects, or pieces of equipment, or things that are
impacted by that,
like they have been by other things in the past, then
let's say it's paving, we just get less paving this year.
We do have fixed prices for fuels at our
fuel depot. I can't remember if there's a clause in there saying if the
United States declares war and that impacts it, then we have the right to
escalate it. But I don't know if you know that, Skip, or-
I'll have to look at my contract.
Yeah. Melissa was here, she'd rattle off the page-
Yeah
... and section that that was on.
You're going to get back to your desk and get an email.
Yeah. I've got- ...
look for a text right now. Nope. So,
some things are fixed from that. But you're right, there will be
definitely expenses that we have that will be more because of that.
Thank you.
All right. Can't wait to hear the other eight.
Awesome.
Anyone else? Any questions? Councillor Pride?
Councillor West, you already asked. Okay.
I just ever the optimist, I have one quick question which is: Is there any
chance that in the governor's supplemental budget just passed, there are
revenue pockets that might come our way?
I know that is actually true for the schools.
For the school, yeah. Not for
us directly as a municipality.
But for the school, there was some good news in that budget.
Okay.
It's good news for us, too.
Yeah. Well, yes, but I meant in addition to. All right.
Thank you so much. Members of the public, I think
you may have some comments about the presentation we've just had.
That isn't Pedro.
HRC usually.
HRC.
Oh, sorry. Oh my goodness, what a faux pas.
Come on up, please, if we're going to hear the presentation.
Thank you, councilors. Pedro Vazquez speaking in my capacity
as the chair of the Southfield Human Rights Commission.
We recognize what a unique opportunity it is to be able to address
you in this way,
regarding our municipal budget, and are very grateful for that.
So, I want to begin by acknowledging the work reflected, in this
proposed budget. As everyone has already said, Scott and his
team do a marvelous job of producing this
document every year.
Municipal budgeting, though, requires difficult decisions, and really
that effort is visible here.
What I'd like to offer tonight is a human rights
perspective on how this budget might be experienced across
our community.
Because as we know, a municipal budget is not just a financial
document, it's one of the clearest expressions of our
values. Not what we say, but in what we fund.
And from a human rights perspective, the central question becomes,
not only whether the budget is balanced, but whether it is
experienced as fair.
So, who benefits from our investments?
Who is burdened by our decisions? And who may be affected
without being present in the process?
This FY 2027 budget is structurally sound.
It reflects continuity. It reflects discipline.
It reflects commitment to maintaining core services.
But it's also a traditional budget in a non-traditional moment.
Right now, as we've been speaking for several weeks now,
parts of our community are experiencing fear,
withdrawal,
and uneven access to public systems.
There's reduced participation in civic life.
And it's within that context of uneven experience and
reduced participation that individual budget decisions
take on additional meaning.
Because even relatively small investments can shape how
systems are experienced.
I just want to offer one quick example that will help illustrate that.
There is a proposed expenditure of approximately
$26,000 for automated license plate
readers,
a technology associated mainly with Flock Safety,
which has been an embattled corporation,
and their
systems have been questioned.
They're controversial to say the least.
And so I want to make sure that you understand that this is not an argument against
public safety. It's a request for alignment.
We're respectfully requesting that this expenditure be subject to additional
review and public discussion before adoption.
And specifically, we're looking for clarification of use,
transparency of the data handling,
clear safeguardsand
accountability
and meaningful community engagement.
Safety is not only enforcement capacity,
it's whether people feel safe engaging with the systems around them,
and we see continued investments in these systems,
but less invisible investment in participation infrastructure,
community engagement, language access, and targeted
support.
We are strengthening systems but not strengthening access at the
same pace.
And so again, we appreciate the work that has gone into this proposed
budget, and recognize what a
magnanimous task it is for it to be produced every year in
such a responsible way. And we hope we continue to ask not only
how this budget performs, but how it is experienced.
Thanks.
Thank you very much.
Sorry, I'm taking my last note.
Okay.
All right. I think now is the time that public comment is opened.
Carlton Parsons,
South Portland, 358 Clarks Pond Parkway.
Good evening, City Council, Portland family, and community members.
I am here as a citizen passionate about
budget and the future of South Portland's community.
I heard at the last city council meeting an excitement of members of our
community to present plans to rebuild our water, clean our community,
and donate money to members of our community who have suffered
at the hands of our weak, cowardly, and fiscally
irresponsible federal administration.
But imagine my disappointment when I heard some of these solutions
from our city council. Hesitancy to invest in a clean,
sustainable water system.
A plan to fire some of our best educators in the state and raise
our unemployment rate. No plans to increase housing
supply, spreading the tax burden, and increasing revenue--
and decreasing revenue without attention to our budget.
One member said that he claimed to represent all taxpayers by
asserting that every single taxpayer cares more about an
accounting line item than our immigrant neighbors who fundamentally
giving them the dignity they deserve.
So every year we fire public workers, raise our unemployment,
lowering the number of taxpayers, market rates rise, and
housing and rents become more unaffordable
with no long-term solution in tight.
We have seen the long-term effects of other towns who prioritize dollars over
people.
Yearly arsenic warnings in public water, closing healthcare
facilities, dying city centers, and residents living for days
without heat or power. The myth of a balanced
budget, of conservatism.
A budget first policy. So here's my
suggestion.
In my hand, there is a $300 check made out
to the city,
increasing the equivalent of a cost of a $12
Big Mac meal per my paycheck. A symbol of what an
impact policy of radical revenue generation can do.
We have nearly 30,000 residents in South Portland.
Here's what just one third of them can do with two Big Mac meals.
10,000 residents,
$250,000 a month, $3
million a year, $30 million in revenue over a
decade.
Your time is up.
Economic investment on par with major cities in a country
without even tapping a majority of our residents.
So what if the wealthiest in our community gave an additional amount, 500,
1,000, 2,000? A contribution less than what the poorest
people in this community offer.
So my proposal is the first of its time.
A progressive property tax rate that will benefit working-class
homeowners and renters, increasing housing supply-
Time
... reducing the rents and market rates.
Benefits for landlords who reduce and lower rates to
families.
I'm here to ask the City Council to consider a different approach,
that we can increase our budget in new and inventive ways, and that
everyone is one of our taxpayers that just
wants to see our city crumble.
Thank you.
Thank you very much. Thank you.
All right. Do we have anyone else that wants to make comment
on the budget presentation?
Ed Cobb, Romano Road.
I looked at this budget last night.
I'm not sure if something changed from last night to this morning, but it looked
like it went down a little bit per se.
But I did want to ask a question, and the question was this: If we
continue at this rate of spending, which seems
to be about 5% to 6% every year, which is double the
inflation rate nationally,
how long before we get to a $10,000 tax bill for the average
homeowner?
And I kind of tried to run the math, and it looked like to me, even
without
adding any of the capital improvements such as the
police station and the fire department at City Mahoney
redeveloped or reimagined or whatever it is these days,
that we'd be there in about seven to eight years.
And I just really want to just have everybody just take a deep
breathAre we ready to have a $10,000 tax
bill for the average homeowner? Because I just don't think
we are, and I think if we continue this
continued path of growth, we're going to be there, and it's not going to take too
long.
The other question I had was in
I believe, the executive's branch.
It looks like we were losing some COVID money,
but we're continuing to spend that money.
I guess it was free money for a while.
Now that money's gone, but we're not removing that
$100,000 that went away. So I'm just wondering why that isn't the
case. And I guess ultimately,
I think
we need to cut that budget pie at least 2%
somehow. And I'm not saying necessarily that it should affect fire and
safety or public safety, but I think as far as,
for lack of a better way of putting it,
the paper-pushing part of the mechanism needs to go down.
The other thing I would mention too is
I get that the healthcare costs went up, but why is it that the
taxpayers are the ones who are burdened with that increase in the
healthcare costs for employees? Why aren't employees
being asked to put in more money?
Just a few questions that I noted. The other last thing I'll mention, too,
and I believe it was mentioned in the budget that we did the whole Metro
Bus
integration with Portland, and it saved $1 million.
I believe it was on last year's budget as well it was mentioned.
But there was no talk about
basically what the State of Maine and their little property tax
committee has come up with where-
30 seconds
... they say we need to share services with other towns.
There was no talk about trying to come up with a shared model where we
share assessing duties for, say, with Portland or Cape Elizabeth or
anything like that. And that's it. Thanks so much.
Thank you very much.
All right.
Come on, keep them coming if you have comments. Thanks.
Hi. Lucy Perkins, I live on Walnut Street.
Like many others, I appreciate and recognize that your job as city councilors is
rarely easy, and the task of balancing municipal and school budgets is
difficult, and hard decisions have already been made to propose the city manager's
budget. So first, thank you for giving this process the care,
thought, and discernment that it deserves to put our tax dollars to the best and
highest use.
Over the next couple of weeks, I hope that as a community, we arrive at a
fair and balanced budget that reflects a commitment to the health and wellbeing of
every person who lives here, that chooses community safety and education, keeping
our schools open with teachers and staff members who care for our students over
surveillance. With that in mind, I'm hoping to simply better understand what
is being proposed in the police department's budget related to Flock
safety. So I have three areas of curiosity where more information would be helpful.
Can you first clarify exactly what the Flock FY27 budget request will be
for? It looks like seven Flock LPR cameras and software
platform. What has already been purchased?
Second, how is the budget request related or not to the existing contract
that the City of South Portland and Flock have?
Would we be signing any sort of contract amendment?
And third, how does this budget request align with the city's priorities, and why
has it been added? Thank you for hearing out and providing answers to these
questions.
Thank you. Thank you very much. Come on, you guys. Come on.
We want to hear from you.
Hi, I'm Olivia Westfall. I live on Hutchinson Street.
I'm also here to talk about Flock cameras.
And I echo everything that everyone has said, thanking you all for the hard
work that went into the budget. This is
proportionally a small budget item, but I think it's very
important. I understand that the intent of the cameras
is for safety, but the more I learn about Flock as a private entity, the more
concerned I am about the extensive data that these cameras can collect
and how the data is being used. I've connected with the
ACLU of Maine, who have been doing research on
ALPR cameras throughout the state and have submitted a FOA
request to many cities in Maine, including South Portland.
Through this conversation with the ACLU and some additional initial
research, it has become clear to me that Flock cameras are being used for
surveillance rather than safety.
Some of the things that have concerned me are the use of Flock cameras by ICE.
Even if our local police department may follow the policy that these cameras are
not to be used for immigration status checks, that does not mean that ICE and
other federal agencies will follow this policy.
Flock cameras are being used to track people seeking abortions in other states,
and many other misuses, errors, and abuses of the system, as well
as just being concerned generally about surveillance.
Many cities and municipalities, both in Maine and outside
of Maine, have ended their contracts with Flock due to all these
concerns. There's way too many to list tonight,
but I'd be happy to follow up over email with the many examples that I listed
of the concerning surveillance usage of Flock cameras, as well as examples of
cities that have ended their contracts for these exact reasons.
I have just three questions around the use of Flock in South Portland, and I think
they're similar to the ones that Pedro asked.
But one is: How is our local police department using Flock?
What searches are being run for external entities, and which external
entities are they? What safeguards are in place to ensure
these entities are using the data in line with South Portland's and Maine's
policies?
And that's all. Thank you so much.
Thank you very much.
Two quick things that your comments reminded me of.
Anyone is welcome to email
comments to the city council members at any time.
And we're going to answer questions at the end of public
comment. All right, any more public comments?
Hi, I'm Alex Redfield on Cooper Street.
After the city manager's presentation, I just did the math and figured out that my
own emails to city staff and online service requests increased by 40% since
2024. And I appreciate the service, and investment, and planning that
goes into that prompt response. Really appreciate the work.
The budget review carries real weight for the future of our city, and thanks to all
of you for digging in. I'd also like to speak to the budget item
around a contract with Flock Safety, a small dollar value, but
outsized in its potential impact to South Portland residents.
Instead of restating the concerns with the company and police department's
relationship with that company, I'd like to call in another element of the budget
line. In South Portland, the ACLU of Maine submitted a
Freedom of Access Act request on November 5th, 2025, seeking information
about the police department's relationship with Flock Safety and the safeguards
that are or aren't in place for residents' data.
Five months later, that information has not been provided.
The delay is concerning, and my question tonight is to see if staff have any
information on the status of that request, as learning more about the nature of
that contract and the commitments contained therein feels like an essential element
of any good oversight in advance of budget decisions.
In Lewiston, a similar FOA request revealed that cameras that had been installed
without the knowledge of many city officials, discovered only when public works
staff stumbled upon a Flock installer tinkering with a traffic light without
permission, prompting intense public scrutiny and a wholesale
reconsideration of the utilization of these cameras.
To quote, and this will be the first and last time I ever quote the conservative
political firebrand Laurel Libby regarding the process in Lewiston.
"This is a process that is playing out across the state and
across the country to the detriment of citizens and their privacy.
These cameras are installed with grant funding, so they're installed without any
citizen oversight. We should always have a say rather than a secretive process that
skirts citizen approval." As a resident of South
Portland, it is difficult to feel confident in this system without a clear public
understanding of how the partnership operates, how the data is protected, and how
decisions have been made. Without additional information, there are reasons to be
concerned about how residents might be tracked without due process and about
whether the contract with South Portland Police Department complies with Maine law
on data use and retention. The contract that was revealed through a separate
FOA request implies that data can be held for 30 days.
Maine state law says individual data should be held for no more than 21 days.
And given the context of all this within South Portland budget cycle, where dollars
are tight and tensions are high, additional spending on a tool that flies in the
face of our ongoing public commitment to protect all South Portland
residents-
30 seconds
... feels especially problematic.
As you proceed through the budget process, I hope you're able to find a little bit
of time and capacity to explore the value and concerns surrounding Flock cameras in
South Portland. Thanks.
Thank you.
Anyone else?
Good evening, Council. John Murphy, Willard Street.
I think we need to
look at this budget, and we need to look at it in a different way, and we need
to look at alternatives that haven't been talked about
and do this with an open mind, because we're looking at-- Let's
take one item. Let's take the golf course.
We're looking at a $200,000 increase to build a ramp.
My understanding was that ramp was replaced less than 20 years ago,
that bridge, as they call it. Why do we have to replace it again at a cost of
200 grand? On top of that, you've got, I believe
Scott said, $250,000 worth of mowers that we're going to buy this year
for the golf course.
Why do we own a golf course? Why does this city own a golf course?
We talk about affordable housing. Get rid of the golf course.
Look at all the housing you can put over there.
We're not in the golf business. We shouldn't
have a golf course.
There's a half a million dollars right there that could come out of the budget.
We don't need a bridge. We don't need a bridge to the library, and we don't need
the golf course. And if we need a bridge after 20 years, who
was responsible for putting it in 20 years ago that it's junk
now?
I think we gloss over some of these things and, oh, it's nice to have a golf
course. Well, Bath had a golf course. They sold it 20, 25 years ago.
Their city didn't crumble.
Selling that golf course could bring in a tremendous amount of
money. And if we decided not to sell it, and we're so bent
on affordable housing,
there's a tremendous amount of land sitting right there, two
feet away from the highway, from access, from all the access you need at Broadway,
at 295 and all that stuff, Washington
Street, Westbrook
Street, I think it is.
We need to start looking at things differently.
This continued tax increases for the average
person in South Portland are unbearable.
And at what point
is it going to be too much? As somebody said, when does it go to
$10,000 for the average house? And most people aren't even in an
average house. So their increase, I love it when they talk about, "Well,
our increase is only going to be $200 for the average house." Well,
that's $200 every year, $400 every year, $600
every year,
and the next thing you know we're at
10 grand for the average household.
That's almost-
30 seconds
... $1,000 a month in taxes. We've got to start looking at
things differently. And
as nice as it is for our community to say, "Yeah, we're going to stand up and help
the people that we're concerned about the ICE agents in town," I don't think
it's my place, and I don't think it's the city's taxpayers' place to
pay $100,000 or $150,000 to pay for
someone's rent.
And on top of that, what kind of safeguards are in place?
We had six, five people, I guess, in South Portland-
Time, Mr. Murphy
... that were arrested or taken by ICE.
How does that translate into $150,000 or 100?
I'm not sure what the number is. It was up to 200 at one point.
But how does that translate into a fairness for the taxpayers?
Are you wrapping up?
We need to look at things differently, I think. Thank you.
Thank you very much. Anyone else on the topic of the
city manager's presentation of the budget?
Okay, I don't see anyone. Generally, I would say public comment
is closed. But I think what you're saying is that we need
to leave it open because of the other item not being presented.
We've noticed this evening's meeting as the public hearing for both the alt
departments presented by the city manager as well as the school.
And since that item is being postponed until the 14th, the council will have to
make a motion to postpone to keep public comment open.
You can close public comment, but then you would have to still motion to postpone
and reopen public comment. So it is entirely the council's decision.
All right. It sounds like it might be neater to close public
comment. Plus, I get to bang my little hammer.
So public comment is closed on the topic of the budget
presentation.
Now, we need to motion to postpone-
Do you want to hear the questions this evening and then motion?
Well, I do. Okay. So we'll wait on the motion. Thank you very much.
All right. So we're going to
scattershot answer to the questions.
So there's a question about
COVID funding and the executive budget.
So back when we received ARPA funds from
the federal government five years back,
one of the small things we used this funds
for were to pay for half of the salary for a new communications
officer and half the salary of a new
purchasing agent or an upgraded position that went from half-time to full-time.
Always very clear that COVID funds would run out, that in FY26 would be the
last year we'd be able to use them. And so after that, it would go on the tax
rate. So,
this has
been one of those things through the years that we've said, "Hey, this is going to
be something that comes on." So unless the council wants to get rid of the
purchasing agent and get rid of the communications director, which we didn't
think they did, and we don't recommend, that money, as we have been
saying all along,
it now goes on to the tax rate.
As terms of how long until the average tax bill goes to 10,000, a
number of factors would go into that.
How much does spending increase each year?
How much do non-property tax revenues come in each year?
How much new growth is there in a community each year to mitigate any sort of
increases in expenses?
A bunch of different factors
in there. Can the city do things to regionalize to save money?
So that's not really a question
that we've done a sort of analysis on, but it would depend on a
number of factors. In terms of healthcare costs, so
like most municipalities, the city pays a percentage, usually a large
percentage of the cost of health insurance for its employees.
Some of it's dictated by contract for the police, fire, public
works unions, which is where most of our employees are.
For non-union folks, it's dictated by the personnel policy approved by the
council. So,
there are some instances, I think few, where
employees' health insurance is covered at 100%.
In most cases, it's a percentage split, 90/10, 80/20.
So the city, if there's a $1,000 increase in the premium,
the city would absorb $800 increase.
The employee would then pay $200,
for example.
I'll get to the flock questions last because there were several of them.
Skip, can you talk a little bit about the ramp to the library and whether it
was replaced 20 years ago, and
what's going on there?
Yeah. Thanks, Scott. Don Hopkins, Facilities Director.
So,
before my time in 2013, I believe I've heard the bridge had
some work done to it. So if anyone's gone by there, you notice they're
very large bridges. They span probably 30 feet, 30 plus feet
across this ravine to the second floor of the library.
And, so when they did the work in 2013, they replaced the
concrete. They didn't actually replace any of the structural steel.
Basically, you have metal decking, and then you pour concrete on top of that, sits
on top of the steel. So that was all replaced back in
2013. None of the structural steel was ever done at that time.
So now what's happened is that structural steel has started to fail where it meets
the building, and the hangers on the building that carry that steel have
all rusted up. It actually almost looks like plywood now.
The steel has started to actually disintegrate
and come apart in layers, which is kind of scary.
So,
we're actually thinking that
if we don't do something quickly, which if we don't get that money to do the
capital, then we'd have to redo something on the top of
that, put plywood on top of it, or just to maintain the structural
integrity so we don't have anybody walking through, falling through the concrete
that's there now. And so the metal decking,
because you have all that rust on the steel itself, that metal decking, even though
it's galvanized, has started to rot away as well.
I have a structural company looking at it and
determining whether it's safe to walk across right now.
But we know that we need to do some work to it to at least get it back up to par
where it would be refinished. And we may have to
replace some of the steel, but we're not real sure of that at this point.
But at least replace some of the pieces that are there and then repaint
and
sandblast the rest of the steel and paint it all so that
it can take care of,
won't be weather and salt and everything else that deteriorates that.
So that's what the 200,000 was for
Carl, if you could come up about golf course.
I'll start off saying, if it wasn't clear in my presentation, just to make sure
it is, golf course isn't funded by any tax dollars.
It's funded completely by the revenue it generates.
It is a
revenue surplus generator, so anything that
we buy, like a mower,
is paid for by the golf fees that people pay.
But maybe you could talk a little bit more about that and whether or not that's a
property. I don't know if there's any deed restrictions on that as a golf course or
anything you could talk about.
Yep. Hi, Carl Coughlin, Parks, Recreation, Waterfront, and Cemetery
Director.
To Scott's point,
the golf course is an enterprise account. It is self-sustaining.
The last two years have been extremely profitable years for the golf course.
I'd say we've generated about a million dollars in revenue over the last
four fiscal years. It's to the point where all of our
capital purchases are being funded through the
golf course's fund balance, so there is no impact whatsoever on the taxpayer.
The golf course itself was purchased using
Land Water Conservation funds back in, I believe, the early
1970s. So I know there are restrictions with that.
Josh, I don't want to put you on the spot, but I know Josh deals quite a bit with
LWCF, and I know that there are restrictions that would
essentially put the city in a bad place with the state's LWCF-
Can I summarize quick, Josh? We'd have to find an equivalent area of
open space if we were to want to develop that and
make that other area this... If it's 20 acres, then we'd have to make
20 acres somewhere else open space and not developable. Is that right?
That's right. It's a long process.
We're going through it right now, actually, with one of the acquisitions we did
to...
Anyway, I don't want to go off on a tangent.
We have a little violation that we're addressing that goes back a number of years.
But that particular property, the golf course, yes, the entirety
of it is restricted with a deed restriction, and it'd
be a long process to convert. It's the process called
conversion to
switch it to another property to
take away that deed restriction. It's evaluated through both its
market and monetary value, but also qualitatively, its
recreational value. So you'd have to find another parcel that is
of equal monetary value and equal or
more recreational value, and anyway, it's a long process to
evaluate that.
There's a question about safeguards in place for the money donated to help
with assistance. So that money was not just for folks
that were
detained by ICE, but it was also intended for folks that were
either afraid to show up to work, leave their homes,
or their place of employment was closed.
And so they didn't have
a place to go to work because either the owners had fears
of immigration enforcement or enough employees weren't able to show up.
And so the agreement that we have with Project HOME is they have a
specific vetting system to confirm
that folks were impacted, and the payment goes directly to
the landlord, not to the person making the application.
So there's proof that there's a lease in place, that this
person lives there, they experienced a hardship,
and the check goes to the landlord, and not the
property owner. And it's only reimbursed
to Project HOME. The city only reimburses them up to
$100,000 if they've spent those funds and met those
criteria.
And now, Chief, we have some questions about Flock.
We have questions about the budget amount in FY27.
Where does the follow request from five months ago stand?
What searches have been done? What safeguards are in
place? Can it be accessed by ICE? What's the existing
contract look like, et cetera?
Dan Hart, police chief.
I prepared a document for you, the city manager,
and I believe we shared that with city council as
well. That answered many of these questions. I can read from it.
I was prepared to do a brief presentation during my budget next
week, but I certainly can try to relieve some of the
concerns by our community members here tonight.
The total budget request, I believe, is 21.5,
21,500. That's for seven cameras.
It basically boils down to a licensing agreement for those cameras
after the... They're not really a purchase. They're kind of like a lease.
Automatic license plate
cameras
that we use currently
are provided by this company called Flock.
Flock has, as some people have
alleged, become this controversial
entity. But I have shared with you many, many
success stories that these cameras have
provided to our community, safeguarding our community.
I truly believe that they are keeping our community safe, that they
do not
target certain individuals. They don't surveil
individuals.
This is a higher surveillance tool than anything
else that you could ever imagine.
Automatic license plate readers do primarily two things.
When an officer
wants to search for a vehicle, a specific vehicle, or a
license plate of a vehicle, we enter that into the Flock
system, if you will.
That system then will tell us whenever that vehicle
or a vehicle that looks like that vehicle, let's call it a black Mercedes
SUV, if we don't have the license plateWe're
searching for a black Mercedes SUV.
I'm using this example because this was the vehicle that was used in the ATM
robbery
that was solved using the Flock cameras.
We put that in, and any time
any black Mercedes SUV
goes by one of these cameras, whether it's in South Portland or another
entity or state that has those cameras, it will give
us an alert. "Hey, that vehicle just went
by the 295 camera
by Westbrook Street,
by the entrance to 295."
It takes a picture of the license plate and the vehicle, not the operator.
We don't know who the operator is. That
information has to be gathered by the officer, who then
can go into the NCI computer, run the plate, and gets the information about the
registered owner for that vehicle.
There's no pictures of people
driving the vehicles. These license plate readers read
license plates. That's the
technology. Don't ask me how it works.
We then can, yes, track that vehicle's,
where it is. We can send
officers that are out to that area to search for that vehicle.
"Hey, it just went by this camera. Anybody in the area?" "Yeah, I'm by the mall."
"Okay, I'm going to look for it." Hopefully stop the vehicle, and we go from there.
So
surveilling
individuals,
keeping information, yes. The information that we gather from
these plate readers are kept for 21 days.
That's main state law. That's law.
That's what we do. That's how we keep it. That's how long we keep it.
I'm trying to remember some of the-
What about searches? Could I just go in and say, "Geez, my ex-girlfriend drives a
white Corvette. I want to track white Corvettes."
Right.
Can I do that?
So,
sure.
Could a police officer use this technology for a nefarious
purpose? Sure,
for that purpose, right? And
I'm sure there have been examples of that, and I think I've read some of those
where officers have been disciplined and fired for that improper use of that.
And I would fire an officer for improper use of this technology.
We-
Is there a log of those searches?
I'm sorry?
Is there a log of those-
There's an audit of all of our searches.
All of these searches are audited. Who did it? When did they do it? From where?
So we have all of that information we can save.
We've been using these cameras for 16 years,
2010?
2010, we've been using automatic license plate readers.
We have policy for it.
If you think about a police officer who's out
there and has their own internal biases, and they're like,
"I want to run that guy. I didn't like what I saw in that car."
Right? "I don't like the look of that car.
It's all beat up." There's some
internal bias. These cameras have none of that.
This is like a force multiplier, it's often defined as, where
you could have a police officer standing on the corner where one of these cameras
is mounted, and they could run, if they possibly could, every
single license plate that goes by, take a picture of it.
Think about the ability of that officer to be able to do that. Can't do it.
Impossible. But these cameras have that ability.
It's like putting a police officer there tracking
stolen vehicles,
missing persons, silver alerts,
abducted children by
sometimes parents,
criminal activity, stolen cars.
I've given you examples of how many of these things that we've been able
to solve just with the use of these cameras.
I want to assure our community that we're not
misusing the cameras. They are
fair. They are equitable. They are safeguarding
all of our community, everyone in our community.
They're an invaluable tool.
But the cost,
frankly, isn't that much money when you really think about
what we're able to do with this technology. And that's what we're doing.
We're
taking advantage of technology.
Can you talk a little bit more about the contract, the amount that is in this
budget? There's one additional
Flock device in it in addition to the how many we have now.
Is that right?
Yeah.
I fully support this thing. I know people are going to probably
jump out of their seats. I wish I had 10 more cameras.
These cameras are invaluable to us.
We have seven cameras now.
We had six, and we had a, what they call a flex camera.
So it was a portable camera that we could use
to put somewhere if we were working on a, let's say, it's called a drug
investigation. We wanted to put a camera somewhere to see if a certain car was
going to a certain residence
often.
We didn't see the real use of that. We didn't see a benefit to that camera, so
we traded it in, turned it in for a
fixed-position camera, another one, and we actually got money
back for that.
Because they
cost less.
There's been some conversation that wasn't brought up
here, like the placement of these cameras.
How did you decide there's cameras
in certain areas of our city that maybe
they shouldn't be in, and they're targeting certain
groups or individuals. The
people from Flock came to us and they said
Let's look at your city. Let's go around your city.
They drove around, they looked at access points.
You want to have these things as
gateways. Who's coming in and out of our community?
Where are they coming in and out of our community?
295, Westbrook, Crockett's
Corner, that's a big area for us to have people coming in and out of the
city.
Is it near Red Bank? Sure it is. Is it targeting? No.
That's why it's chosen. That's the reason we chose that
location.
Maine Mall Road, in and out, 95. That's why you choose
those locations. We listen to the people from Flock that say,
"From our experience, this is
the best way to get the most
pictures that you can." So that's what goes into
choosing the locations of these cameras.
Chief, in terms of monitoring people, we've heard some people
at No Kings protests have been monitored and followed.
Do we have-
Yeah.
There's no monitoring.
It just simply doesn't happen. We don't do that.
Again, what we decide to put
in that system to search for and tell us,
"If you see this vehicle cross one of these cameras,"
that's all the information you get.
I mean, is it lawful to do that?
I don't know.
I'm sorry?
Is it
lawful to track people for protesting under Maine law?
I would say that it's
a violation of their constitutional rights.
I don't have any complaints about that.
I haven't heard anybody come to me.
Pedro, we have a really good working relationship.
So no one's come to me and said, "I have a
complaint that my constitutional rights were violated because I believe,
the South Portland Police Department is monitoring my
activities at rallies or wherever."
I don't have the Maine Human Rights Commission
notifying me of any complaints.
The evidence that I have is that this is a positive
tool that's giving us positive results in
safeguarding our community, and that's it.
Last, I didn't hear about the FOA. Any idea why it's taken five
months?
I don't know. I'll have to do some research on the FOA request.
Someone said that the ACLU
created a FOA request for us? For what?
For I-
I'm wondering, like for the Flock contract, is that what it was for, just the
contract itself?
And then the correspondence too.
Yeah.
The contract? I mean, the contract is-
It's not the contract, it's communications between Flock and the police
department, and a request for the audit logs that was provided from-
Oh. Hey, I'm all about transparency.
I'll sit here and show you the logs.
I'll come up here and we'll do it. We'll put them up on the screen.
You can all see it.
I am all about that. I really want to be transparent about this because
it's such a good tool.
And it's not
harming us. It's safeguarding us.
It really has been magical what we've been able to
do, to find people
from Augusta. Hey, this
85-year-old gentleman left in a Buick LeSabre, and
we haven't seen him in... And he hits a Flock camera at the mall, and we go find
him parked at the mall. I mean,
it doesn't get better than that for us.
Thanks, Chief. Last thing I'll say too is in South Portland, might not be the same
in other communities, but in South Portland, when we get a grant, which we did to
purchase the initial
five or six Flock cameras, those do appear on council agendas and get
approved publicly, so there is awareness.
It's not something that staff applies for and does, and then cameras go up
without anyone's knowledge or having an approval
process that goes through the public.
Okay. So I think we have a couple of
comments that we need to hear, but I also just wanted to ask a
procedural question. Chief, you mentioned that you had planned to do a
presentation. So I believe that's when we're talking about the police
department budget. What is the date for that?
Yeah, I know I have 10 minutes, but I've got another thing that I have to put in
front of you on that night, too, as a request that got deleted from the
budget. So I know I'm going to be pressed for time, but I can do a very
brief
presentation
on the Flock cameras as well,
if that would be helpful.
Okay, because I thought I also heard one more question.
I know it's a question that's out there as it relates to these cameras, which is
security for the data that's collected.
Right. So I just want to read a couple of quick things, and I know I'm taking up
time here, people, get away.
So can other law enforcement agencies or organizations
access our Flock cameras or data without our knowledge? No.
Other law enforcement agencies or organizations cannot access our
Flock
cameras or data without our knowledge.
By default, our agency is defaulted to only be
discoverable for sharing at a 50-mile statewide radius,
and no one
outside or organization can see our cameras or data unless
we accept a sharing request from them.
This discoverability only means we can receive requests
from them and then choose how to respond.
So yes, could ICE reach out to me and say, "Hey,
we want to see that camera footage"?
Then it's got to go through me.
That's the safeguard. So we have an automatic default in our
settings that no one can see our data, no outside
agency, unless we allow it.
Okay. At this point, I think our council and our
councilor
would like to be recognized.
Well, I was just going to ask that question, and he answered it.
Oh, okay.
Was who-
If you wish
... who has access to our data?
Sure.
Because I think that was the main thing people wanted to know.
Yes. Thank you.
I can just provide maybe a high-level
status update in terms of the FOIA request to maybe
save the chief some time. My understanding as of last week
in my correspondence with
Janet at the police department, that they were still waiting on the check
from the requester in order to start processing it.
So when there's a FOIA request, there's an estimated cost to review those documents
above and beyond the two hours, and I think as of March
30th, we're still waiting for the payment in order to process the
review of those documents.
Thank you for that update. Very useful.
I'm always available. You know where I work.
Come to me, and I will bring you into my office, and we'll pull it up on my
computer.
Full access, full welcome. Come in, see me, bring a cup of coffee, and
we'll go through it. Anybody who wants to see it.
All right. Councilor Coleman, let's recognize Councilor Coleman, but then I think
it's going to be time to bring this to a close.
My question is, does Flock have access to the data
it's collecting? Because that was like a- Yes, it is
secured by Flock. Yes. But do they have
access? Yeah, but they don't.
So we're trusting them is what you're saying? Well, let's see.
Is there a backdoor, or can Flock- Yeah ...
quietly change the logs?
No. There is no backdoor access for any agency.
Audit logs are designed to be complete, transparent,
and reviewable. Entries are written automatically,
retained for oversight, and cannot be quietly edited or
overwritten. Changes to sharing or settings
appear as separate events, not hidden
modifications.
What do our Flock edit logs capture and are searches justified?
Our audit tools capture who searched when, what
they searched,
which can review and, if needed, share with appropriate
oversight bodies. Searches
are tied to the standardized NIBRS-based offense type, so
there is a clear public safety justification
documented for every search. Can't just, "Hey, I want to search
because I want to know who's parked at my girlfriend's house." Right?
You got to put in there why, the reason for your search.
Why are you looking for this car?
Okay.
Thank you.
We look forward to
reviewing the police department budget when it is time to do that and
hearing all kinds of good information. Thank you.
At this time, with questions answered,
I think that we have to postpone the school
discussion. So I need a motion to
postpone.
I need a motion to postpone what
is called the superintendent of schools
proposal, but I don't think it's supposed to be called that.
So not sure what to do about that except to amend
the postponement because I believe when it comes to us
after the school board has passed it, it's called the school board's
budget.
Is that just nothing anyone cares about?
That is simply how it's titled on the agenda.
The notice is for the public hearing of the budget.
Okay.
That's what we are posting.
Let's call it that then.
Yeah, it's just-
All right. Can we have a motion to postpone that to
April 14?
Yes. I move to postpone the public hearing for the school portion of the
budget to April 14.
Well done. Thank you. Do we have a second?
Second by Councilor Walker. All in favor?
All right. That is finished